[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right buckle up everyone
because uh we're about to begin welcome
to the stoa i am peter limberg the
steward of the stoa
and the stow is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this
very moment uh so i imagine some of you
will be new here at the stoa
um in attendance right now and watching
so just to
give a little preview of uh overview of
what the stoa is
it's kind of hard to define uh sometimes
i call it a communal podcast
but we do have a wisdom gym here as well
essentially it's an online event space
uh and we opened for spiritual business
when kovit came online and we have over
probably 400 events at this point and um
lots of interesting characters coming in
uh noam chomsky's coming in in a couple
months
and uh today we have a very interesting
philosopher
alexander dugan um he's dubbed
in western media as the the most
dangerous philosopher in
the world which we'll talk about in a
moment and
how he came on my radar i think was
about two years ago uh so i was baptized
as a eastern orthodox christian
and i was like researching it getting
into the faith and somehow dugan came on
my
radar and as people at the stone know i
have a pretty jazzy philosophical
background
and i saw this guy he has like a
anti-liberal streak he
weave post-modern thinking into his
philosophy so uh and he has this like
you know this crazy russian beard that
would make any
western man jealous if they saw it so
this all gave me
pause and uh so i looked into him and um
i i saw michael millerman who was a
university of toronto uh who's doing his
phd there
studying dugan uh me and michael
eventually became friends
michael uh came to the store previously
um
and that got me plugged in to read more
about the fourth
political theory uh which we'll be
talking about today
so i imagine we have a mix of people um
that are new to dugan and maybe some are
experienced with dugan's thoughts
so i thought we would come to terms
today with a lot of the stuff
um and get an overview of the fourth
political theory and then we can go
uh dive deep uh with uh with the thought
so how today is going to work i'm going
to chat with dugan for about 10 20
minutes
pop your questions in the chat box
anytime i will call on you you will mute
yourself you ask your question to dugan
if you don't want to be on youtube
because this will be on youtube
indicate that in the chat um so
that being said i will allow duken to
unmute himself
uh and you have to meet yourself again
uh sir
so how are you doing today professor
dugan
uh hello everybody
nice to to to be here so nice to invite
me
and um i would like to say
maybe some words about
fourth political theory because
we are supposed to discuss that today
so first political theory is a kind of
mixture
of anti-or counter-modern
traditionalism with post-modern
and anti-modernism so that is
a kind of bridge between
the radical criticism of the modernity
from the right
from the pre-modern point of view
advocating the sacred tradition
pre-modern values
transcendence hierarchy pre-democratic
estates empire and
all the values and political
philosophical
scientifical um sense
that uh were previous to the
uh modernity
before enlightenment before modern
science that it is advocating
uh of uh uh the values
totally abandoned mocked
uh at a and rejected
with the um arrival
of the modern western
paradigm so that is the kind of
advocating everything that
was pre-modern in the west and
that is not modern and western
outside of the west that is a kind of
one part and second part of fourth
political theory
or the premises of the for preconditions
for a fourth political theory is
acceptance of deconstructing of the
modernity in the
uh postmodern way
of thinking basing on heidegger
and uh lacan theories
uh de los bataries everything that
destroys modernity
from the post-modern position or
pre-modern musician
for pre-modern position should be
uh used in order to deconstruct
modernity the difference between
traditionalism
and for political theory is precisely
that
appeal to the uh radical criticism
from the left of post-modernism uh in
front of the modernity and what
is different the main difference between
fourth political theory and
post-modernism
that appeal to re-affirmation of
pre-modern values destroyed by the
modernity and taken for granted
granted as something totally totally
terrible by
post-modernist so that is a kind of a
mixture
and uh so that is a kind of the
um effort to
encircle the modernity from all
sides from the future with
post-modernism
and from the past to to identify
modernity
to put the modernity in the in the
concentration
camp some of some type to put it to
limit it
to to bring the modernity
and the some concrete limits outside
of those limit should be developed
new alternative way of political
thinking
and that means why fourth political
theory that means
that uh that is invitation to regard
three main uh political theory of
western modernity liberalism communism
and the fascism
or nationalism as the organic parts
of this uh modernity so it is not
the i only anti-anti-liberal
criticism it is anti-liberal criticism
but at the same time it is
anti-communist
and anti-fascist so idea is that
three main political theories of the
western modernity
with all the combination with all the
combination
left liberalism right liberalism left
fascism right fascism
uh communism socialism social democracy
trotsky's everything all that
has according to this analysis uh
all this have this the same common
denominator
that belongs to the western modern
vision of the nature of the reality
of the imminence of the materialism of
the individualism
on the democracy and the
anti-hierarchical
construction uh from the uh
bottom to the top that is the and
that is uh in uh all three political
theories
uh dominating in the modernity
a deal all three of them deal with the
same
cartesian subject it could be individual
in liberalism
it could be class in the communism it
could be nation
or race or state in the fascism or nah
or national socialism so the uh idea
of fourth political theory is to destroy
this cartesian
uh subject this uh rescogence
and to return to everything that
preceded these modern subjects
for example the concept of of the
creationism of the man as the image of
the god
from the right or some uh
heidegger and design or the concept
of the rhizomatic rhesmatic pluralism
in the los angeles everything that is
not modern is accepted all everything
that
is modern is rejected modern in all
three
political or i ideology
dominating in the modernity so it is
anti-liberalism
anti-communism or socialism anti-fascism
and the common denominator of these
three political theories dominating in
the last centuries
is precisely they were burn
burn in the west with
um a modernity with uh
and was the uh was the break
where's the pre-modern western western
values
and concept and philosophies and
that was with colonizational process
was expanded to all the other
part of the planet that where
these main form of modernity was imposed
so that today we could not say that is
just revolt against the modernity of the
west
that is revolt against everything that
is western and modern
as well outside of the of the west
because
today in india in islamic world and
africa
and latin america everywhere almost
everywhere we are dealing with the
western modernity
so that is uh taken for granted
that we we deny uh
public dimension of the religion
we are in favor of liberal democracy we
accept
individualism as the basis of political
correctness
and now with the first political theory
liberalism has gained after the fall of
the communism the memento
so that is the unique today but
that why it's so important for political
theory
because if we reject for example
liberalism and many and more and more
and more today
reject uh liberalism they fall into the
trap
or uh either to communism
or leftist criticism or
nationalism as right populism uh growing
in the world so uh uh
uh rejecting the political modernity
in the form of liberalism that is
uh uh the the only the main
ideology today we're filling into the
trap
into other version of the modernity
either
communist socialist or or fascist
and both or nationalists and both of
them
are part are products of the same
concept of modern subject or the same
materialism on the same
world vision same imminence some plus
the same materialism
and the some the same concept of this
western modernity and the politics that
is more or less
uh the main idea for political theory
so that is idea to encircle western
political modernity
to to elaborate the criticism of
its philosophical and ideological
metaphysical premises
and to reject everything it seems that
it is pure nihilism so if we if we
abandoned political midwestern political
modernity
what we still can have
and my idea is we can have everything
we can have western pre-modern
political ideas platonism aristotle
christianity uh uh byzantine
uh vision of catacomb of
symphony of the power and the orthodox
tradition we can have
catholicism we can have including some
protestant concept
of the state with transcendental
dimension
or roman empire or some
ethnic uh mixture of
kind of middle ages form
of different levels of
of power and we could accept
uh islamic rule islamic politics
chinese confucianism indian
african so we can accept everything
and we can finally accept western
political modernity
but put not as universal
universal pattern uh that is necessary
that is imposing that his own
one and only form of political uh uh
political assault but regarding
regarded as one special
example or possibility uh among
many other options so that is detailed
rising of the political modernity making
a political modernity optional so we can
accept that if you want we can reject
that
but if you say to liberals or to
communists or to fascists that we are
going
to reject uh the universal
value of this political modernity
everybody all three political theory
will be
uh very aggressive because they are
based
on the total return attitude in the case
of communism
and in the case of fascism it is clear
and explicit that these two kind of
regime
i have lived in one form of this
communist
communist spirit that was really
totalitarian
ideologically totally ideologically
it is absolutely obvious that species
was as well the other kind
of this totalitarianism and that was
clear and explicit
now we are living in the liberal
totalitarianism
that is more and more explicit as well
that was implicit fighting against
communism and fascism but after the
victory
of the last totalitarian form of soviet
union
now the liberalism as the paths of
political modernity
and racist attitude of the west imposing
its own values as something universal
it's open
and transparent and clear so that is the
third totalitarianism and all kind of
political modernity
uh is totalitarian is racist
is based on the dictatorship of
one thought uh communists individualists
capitalists or nationalists that is only
one thought and only one
criterium so the first political theory
is against
all kinds of universalisms
all kind liberal against liberal
universalism against communist
universalism
against nationalist racism western
ethnocentric form of any kind and that
is the defense of the pluralism it
doesn't mean that for example
russian values are better than islamic
or
than western absolutely no but russian
values for example
monarchy uh symphony of the power
has a right to exist if we choose that
without regard to what the west for
example
or the liberal presumed to be universal
that that is more or less
um the main frame of fourth political
theory it is not
this theory as such it is just
invitation to
to to to think uh
accepting this thesis and to develop
all kind of alternative discourse all
kind so that is
the the anti-liberal anti-communist
anti-fascist pluralism anti-western
anti-modern pluralism pluralism
and plurality multi-polarity possibility
to
accept everything that is human has not
underdeveloped uh or maybe
designed to repeat the western
uh history it is just a kind of
application of the
anthropological principles to all
modern political uh landscape more or
less that
is that is the main idea and uh
the philosophical aspect in it is to
destroy
they can strike better they can strike
the modern subject
of rene descartes deconstruct
to say it is just one of the possibility
among many other to consider the
humanity the human
identity for example and heidegger and
criticism
of the modernity category and the
destruction
uh uh analytical design can be
a kind of kind of
main main line to follow uh
and uh absolutely not as something
universal not
to replace uh not designed should
replace
uh traditional western uh rescordance of
frenetic art
but uh heidegger analysis is just
example how it could be done how how we
can
deconstruct the western philosophy the
western science and phenomenology
in general how we you can use heidegger
and
philosophy and phenomenology of brentana
jose and other phenomenologists how we
could use phenomenology in order to
deconstruct
the the western uh modernity and
to to to to confront with
some pre-modern post-modern nor no
not western and not modern type of
political thought
everything is accepted including
the the same western political modernity
is
is not rejected is put as something
optional uh the main idea is
to to to liberate
the liberalism from its totalitarian
aspect
liberate socialism and fascism from
its totalitarian racist attitude toward
the
enemy of open society enemy of
proletarian class
or iron race all these kinds of
totalitarian
way of thought explicit today including
in the
last form of political modernity
represented in the globalism
in the liberalism so that is should be
accepted as just optional liberalism
optional
modernity optional you we can choose
modernity
absolutely but we could refuse that is
the problem
we could accept we could reject but
we could in the liberal liberal way of
thought
we could accept liberalism
and we could not accept it
otherwise we are done so we will be
considered the enemy
of uh open society and built
accordingly so as for example the last
point
my youtube accounts recently was
cancelled my google email was recently
cancelled
now last week my twitter account was
canceled
and my books and fourth political theory
is prohibited to distribute through uh
amazon so post service google service is
not just
to to search it is just political
censorship so if you're liberal
if you agree with these liberal
universalism
welcome to use all that if you disagree
with that you have no right
you you will be d platform with no
reason with no
with no explanation at all that is just
confirmation of my ideas so i
i'm not i know uh i i i'm not deploring
that so it's just everything fits very
well
in order so thank you for for your
attention and i can
uh develop this course or answer
uh your questions great great thank you
um yeah you covered uh most of my
follow-up questions
but um i wanted to double click on the
the fourth political theory as you
mentioned uh you said it was an
invitation
many times um and the the subject line
of the
first three political theories or the
the subject of choice the individual
race and class in contrast the fourth
political theory uh
you said the subject there is da sein um
i don't know if i fully grok that and i
understand what you're saying what it
could afford us
but maybe you can kind of speak more
about what that means to you and why you
chose that particular
um term of design
yeah yes so
that was according to my
understanding we could not uh
uh we could not just return to the
pre-modernity or at least in order to
return
to the pre-modernity we need to prepare
the ground that and uh there are already
some historical battle when the
monarchies
the christians the secretary the
defenders of the
middle ages uh way of political
organization have lost their battle
so we we should revise that we should
uh return to to that moment but we could
not do that
in in the uh without understanding the
logic of modernity we could not do that
without uh asking ourselves
why the modernity and that um
traditionalists and conservatives
generally
lack this why modernity they say oh
modernity is bad
let's uh resist the modernity and they
the conservatives and traditionalists
they just follow
follow modernity saying or not not
such speed please please um
not so um slow please slower
slower please so it's not not today
maybe tomorrow so
that is just reactionary so the defense
of the prem modernity
is just reactionary without
understanding
why modernity what is the reason what is
the telos in aristotle and
turns and heidegger provides something
different
he deconstructs modernity
he he makes from modernity a kind of
logical moment
and development of the history of the
western of the west
and of the western thought and western
philosophy that precisely
is abandoning and forgetting
uh of the concept or the idea of being
so this
the process to forget the question of
being
is something logical and according to
heidegger that
is a kind of explanation of this
modernity
so what is modernity this complete
complete oblivion of the
question of being and the previous
previous uh previous uh periods
stages of the western philosophy were
a kind of preparation in the same in the
same
in the same direct direction and when
heidegger
proposes to get out from this situation
not just returning to the past not
not in the reactionary way but proposing
new beginning
so to understand to grasp the meaning
why we have for uh forgotten uh
the the being the west and how we need
and where we
should uh uh find it
or once more and that is precisely
everything is connected to design
concept so we
we should deconstruct all kind of
western subject philosophical of modern
uh and we need to to rely on design
in order to to to put
once more the question of being so we
need to start
with the most profound in my opinion
pro problem and on that
uh basis to develop uh as well
fourth political theory as application
as praxis
practical aspect of this new philosophy
of new beginning
and returning to authentic existence of
the
design of design
self of design should replace
alienated subject that is rather
dasman in heidegger and turn that is
main idea that is why
does i but speaking wisdom
disciple of heidegger professor hermann
in freiburg some years ago i have
suggested
uh the idea that there is as well in
heidegger
one very important thing he told
heidegger that design is universal but
and
my in my opinion it is not design
uh depends on their culture on the
civilization
and we have spoken with for hermann that
heidegger
uh wouldn't accept
these multiplicity of designs
this multitude of designs because
heidegger was
somehow linked to only the western uh
western form he was very critical and
very
innovative uh criticizing western
modernity but
still he was the part of this western
universalism
uh you know but in a very special thing
so there so there is a
very very important shift uh in
my reading of gei dagger i have
dedicated to that
problem my book on russian design that
is now translated by
our friend michael millerman uh he has
finished their translation
where i uh i i've tried to apply
heidegger and concept of design to
russian uh
identity and i have uh come to the
conclusion that
many many uh existentials
should be changed uh applying to
so we could not apply cardigan
understanding of design
to the designs of other culture because
we have different relation to
death we have different relation to uh
to to the horror to the
care and other existential aspects so
uh my understanding of um
design is um
plural heidegger as well he has spoken
about german
design and that was totally that is what
legitimate
but when he say design is unique he
thought that west
the german design is western design
western bazaar is universal design the
same
the same attitude of the uh uh
european ethnocentrism in my opinion
there is
german design there is western design
that is
there is different totally chinese
design
russian design indian design african
design and maybe
inside of these cultures and
civilizations
we could identify the other kinds of
designs so my second definition of the
subject
of fourth political theory is the people
the people not society not ethnic groups
race absolutely nor class nor individual
but uh uh community of the destiny
sharing the same existential identity so
they design on one hand and the people
as the um philosophical concept
as well abandoned in the modernity we're
dealing with individual we're dealing
with
race we're dealing with nation with
state with class with society
but not with the people and the people
from renaissance uh still is
in the heart of our constitution so our
interpretation of
modern constitutions is a kind of user
patient ideological user patient
of the concept of the people because for
liberals
people is the sum of liberal individuals
for
communist that is the form of class and
uh nationalists uh the people is
political nation
but people neither is uh this uh one of
this
thing it is community of this uh
of the uh shared exis existence
of shared cultural identity
based on the same more or less the same
relation
uh to to death so that is existential
concept
uh thank you professor dugan we're we're
now going to
pivot to the q a um when i call on you
unmute yourself uh unless you indicate
it otherwise you'd like me to read on
your behalf
there's a lot of smart people in this
room and i'm sure you can ask tough but
respectful questions
this is not a debate um you got one
follow-up question
if i'm generous i may give you another
one but uh just keep it at
uh one follow-up have that in mind so um
i'll take an arielle first
well yeah thank you so much professor
dugan this is fascinating
uh i guess what comes to mind is i i see
the the criticism or the criticism
you're drawing when it comes to like
liberalism and
and communism but when it comes to
fascism i i guess i do see fascism as
being more
of a romantic movement and some people
you could see it more as like kind of
almost encircling
liberalism from like the future and the
past in a way that you're sort of
describing fourth political theory so
i'm wondering if you could maybe
elaborate on the similarities and
differences between fourth political
theory and fascism
okay so uh uh i consider the fascism
as um the part
of political modernity and that i am
following
analysis of um
of or idea
analysis that totalitarianism
is not um a pre-modern but
modern phenomenon of hana aaron i'm
following in that understanding
hana aaron and i think that fascism
is based on the same alienation as
liberalism
and communism but instead
of the subject uh or individual or class
the fascism is dealing with the nation
but what is
the nation for example nation is the
bourgeois concept
that has appeared at the end
of the middle ages and has replaced the
concept of the
estate of the church of the
empire of the small peasant
community and that nation was based on
individual individual citizenship so
appeal to the nationalism that is clear
the basis of the fascism and national
socialism
is in my opinion already
already the essential part of political
modernity so
i'm rejecting fascism as nationalism
next i am absolutely rejecting
racism in all kinds in biological racism
the color of skin racism
class racism technological racism
because in my opinion we could not
measure the different um
different human societies by
hierarchy between them so
archaic people or developed people
rich people or poor people
we could not compare basing
on the on the criteria taking from
borrowed from
one of them so for example uh we we
could not because uh
uh in my opinion all all peoples
create their own systems of value they
are
incompatible we could not income
measurable
they are totally uh original and
the idea of racism is to declare
that one race or one techno
technological
culture or one one system of values
or one civilization is
higher than other so racism
in my opinion is precisely something
modern because we could not find the
racism
in middle ages we couldn't fight fire
find slavery slavery in um
in uh middle ages all these kind of
racism
or slavery is based
on the western practices of the
modernity so
it could seems i am uh i many times
i was accused to be uh
a guy in favor of fascism but
that is absolutely not so i'm using
heidegger i'm using avala
i i'm appealing to carl schmidt or ernst
junga
as well as to foucault as well as to
to the laws as well as to freud
to to jung to many other
uh uh other authorities but uh
liberals uh trying to to undermine
uh my position try to reduce my position
to to kind of third political theory but
if you
look just look in my book first
political theory
you will find the criticism of
the third political theory of
nationalism fascism
so i uh see uh people
was not in the center of none of uh a
third political theory
nation state race and not the people
because the people it is not a political
construction
it was something a kind of something
original
something sacred and spiritual that was
abandoned
in the beginning of the uh political
modernity so
uh more than that i think that
the main uh the the the
wars of the political modernity is
totalitarianism
uh and racism precisely it could be
openly in the whites man against other
as in
hitler or germans against uh all but
it could be as well in the class because
if we try to only proletarian
other revolutionary class but peasantry
for example in
our east history was considered to be
uh that should be exterminated and that
was the practice of
bolshevik that was as well the kind of
racism class racism
and i think that now liberals behave
themselves
as racists because they say the first
class people
are developed western western
civilization
and everybody who share the same values
all through the world and they impose
their
multiculturalism values liberal values
political correctness
uh through council cultures through
their transforming imposing
obliging the other demonizing every
everyone who is against that that is
liberal racism so
i am against all kind of racism i am
against
nationalism and i am against modern
state
so finally i think that uh reversal
from the globalism to the modern state
it's not solution absolutely
i'm in favor uh not state um
organization or of the society that can
be
empire something more much more and
sacred than state
or that could be anarchist communities
small anarchist communities so it is not
not the state that is uh in my opinion
uh a kind of concept that should replace
liberal globalization so in that sense
if you
put that together there is nothing uh
or the fascism or nationalism in this
opinion and all that
i am i'm saying in all my
writings so i am against the west
because the west is fascist
because the west is racist because the
waste
tries to impose its values as
universal that only only one
one reason for that and the last thing
when amazon or people
were asked why they don't distribute my
books
they have answered because
uh dogen is freshest i have asked
one of my um far-right
person one of the right person in
italy in rome uh the chief of liberia
europa
uh how he can
could deal in the distribution of his
his purely nationalist fascist new
precious books on amazon he has uh
answered no problem
so no problem so i could distribute
everything so
i am censored for fashion
professions that i don't share
absolutely with
the full liberty to distribute the real
fascist books on the same amazon that is
very important they try to
to describe me uh in order to not to to
enter in discussion they they try to
to to impose this wrong image that
for example when the people as michael
millerman
and the other people in in in other
countries
in israel when they uh
come to to to know or my
real writings they were very astonished
so they could find
nothing that could justify such such
a such idea so i have
uh now i have i just mentioned uh
uh enumerated main points
of disagreement fundamental disagreement
were
with third political theory so and that
is not just for talk
of today so everything that is in my i
have written more than 60 books so
in my 60 books and more than that i
i i'm affirming only that
so no nothing to to to
i'm nothing to to to to
we cannot find uh uh any
any place in that in favor of
third political theory but uh
uh for liberals it's an uh
almost impossible impossible to
imagine anti-liberal
being neither communist nor nor fascist
is impossible in their
ideological ideology that couldn't
couldn't exist
that is unrealistic so they prefer
to describe myself as crypto fascists
as hidden fascists and maybe would be
fascist and something like that so that
is the the easiest way to
to to to discard any
any serious argument so but when
we come to to the principles it's not so
easy to
to reject them because partly i agree
partly i agree with pluralism or
multicultural culturalism i
i advocate that so but not in the
liberal way
so i think that there i i make
absolutely against all kind of racism
and uh when i say that for example i
have made many interviews with
cnn bbc many of them when
they they show only the fragments they
judge could discredit me all the other
is cancelled so
that is as soviet union i i was uh i
lived in soviet union i know how that
work it works
that is just the censorship so you put
from answers what
fits uh to your main concept
you put aside everything that doesn't
fit
for example i was asked whether a
russian
russian government financed trump's
american campaign i have said yes oh
all the cameras are on everybody want to
to to know details we i i have uh
uh uh explain as long as i know uh
our oligarchs have uh sub um
have fun have financed uh hillary
clinton campaign
uh thinking that she uh was going
to to win all the camera immediately
stopped
uh nothing uh known this part of the
interview
is cut so uh they they they show
only what they want to show so
that is one that's pure totalitarianism
and
the same with passions so if i i say
something that could be
compared with third political theory i
am
welcomed to to continue if i
start criticism of fascism all the
camera
uh uh uh went off
there is no no no no no no nothing
follows
so that is the way of totalitarian
cancer culture and that is precisely
that shows that we are dealing with
liberalism as with ideology and ideology
is based on the cancelling the opponent
we are
i am considered to be enemy of uh open
society
i am and i could uh
accept that i am an enemy of open
society because i think that open
society is totalitarian
liberal concept so in that sense
i could be judged for that i don't like
popper i think that is the way that uh
justify a kind of uh uh justify
repression against ideological uh
ideological uh
opponents and that is not uh acceptable
but uh i am uh i'm
very very critical uh toward all kind of
nationalism
fascist and uh above all racism
so that is my position when i'm accused
of something i'm guilty
of i could easily accept that for
example i am guilty to be
a liberal i am anti-liberal radically
anti-liberal but i'm
that's at the same time i am absolutely
anti-fascist anti-nationalist and more
than that
radically anti-racist
all right um so we got tons of questions
and they're like amazing questions in
the chat
um i think we were originally scheduled
for 60 minutes and we're coming up
like 10 minutes are you cool to stay 15
30 minutes after the hour uh
dugan or yeah that's great okay no no
pressure
so if you have anyone just leave at the
hour you can leave so if you want to
stay for another half hour then
we'll you can do that you got your
question um
rain you had a question above uh on
universalism
yeah thank you um
so i'm looking at the way that the
fourth political theory as you've
described it incorporates
the deconstructionism of modernism
and um specifically targets at modernity
and deconstructs modernity
and um the way that that
um post-modernism sort of does that in
the name of justice it says there's
these
dominator hierarchies we're going to
deconstruct
all the hegemonic structures um and it
has this notion of justice or equality
or
or deconstructing power and
um i hear that you've adopted the
deconstructionist
approach and applied it to modernity but
i haven't heard you talk about
um what i think is sort of the better
part of post-modernism is
the sensibility of a better world and
the sensibility of
of justice so um and and they've
in my in my belief you know made the
mistake of
having as you describe it these
totalitarian censorship policies
totally agree and yet um where do you
include
sort of the the raison d'etre of the
deconstruction the idea that it's
meant at least in the liberal sense it's
meant to
create a more just world so
i think that um first of all i think
that the concept of justice
or justice is not modern at all it's
very very traditional
and there are many many uh form of
understanding
of justice for example we now we
we think the justice more or less as
a kind of a kind of um
equality but for example
in jewish tradition justice
is power and force it's judgment
justice and the the the beauty
and the goodness it's pardon so justice
is
not against unjustice justice is against
the patterning so to to pardon to
to to uh to to get some to give
something
for we don't deserve so justice is again
the gift
just justice is the uh rigorous attitude
and the gift or pardon it
is a good attitude so justice is very
very special
special in greeks as well and stoics
and aristotle and platinus they
considered
justice precisely as well as this
jewish tradition spiritual tradition it
was considered to
to be a kind of uh very
very um strong and
limitating concept rather than uh
everybody's
happiness and the free distribution of
that
first so uh um justice in the
in in politics it is as well the concept
of the left
in equalitarian science and
postmodernism
is marked by this leftist tradition so
it is in favor of the egalitarian
concept of justice
but if we regard uh
zilda loves uh and guatem
above all concept we see not the justice
we
see uh the will to the uh
uh to nothing as strong
will to nothing and pure
uh liberation of all kinds of
sub-rational desires rather than
justice it is just the liberating
of the uh um
post-individual or kind of divide all
the partly fragmented self
that the splitting of self and the basis
of the the small and chaotic
design desires
manifested as rhizomatic network that
was
not justice because there is no normal
human
subject it is a kind of
kind of uh reaction against
humanism against individualism and
against humanism
but that is very uh a very particular
uh uh thing and about deconstructing
the term and the concept was introduced
in the first pages of zion on site
of heidegger so it was uh uh
taken by jerida uh jack derida
after but the main concept of
deconstruction
was to put precisely philosophical idea
in the historical context
defined by the process of living
of the being that was the initial
uh uh meaning of deconstruction and
uh uh or destruction or destruction and
heard of destruction
and after that that was uh as many other
hyderabad concepts
was uh this concept was borrowed by
postmod uh post modernism and i um
my reading of post-modernism i take i
pick up everything that is heidegger and
there are so many things heidegger and
insert
and laws and i'm trying to to
restore their original phenomenological
uh uh sense so that is my ring of post
modernism but i think that
justice uh depends on the culture
so i i am in favor of justice but for
example
the russian understanding of justice
can be very different from chinese
understanding of
justice so i am pluralist as well
in that sense so i think the justice in
all
all the peoples that is the real values
liberalism
has nothing to do with justice that is
very important
they don't speak about justice because
the or
either liberty or justice liberalism
chooses liberty and illiberalism
left mostly left it chooses
just so in that sense i am choosing
casuals
rather justice and that i'm where i
where i find that as the positive value
i'm
rather inclined to be with such demand
for more justice or for justice
uh and liberty as well i for me
uh in the liberals understanding
it is not not the value because it is
totally negative
that's just liberty from all kind of
collective identity i'm in favor of
collective identity
and speaking with mill john stuart mill
i'm in favor of freedom
but against liberty i am defending the
freedom
and justice but not liberty as this
individualism
but uh uh with one remark that
justice should be put in the historical
and cultural
context because if we just try
to translate the concept of justice for
example in some african language
or in chinese or in indian
sanskrit for example or try to find
something in islam
we will be or in judah judaic tradition
we will immediately
uh uh in totally different concept
we could not for example we could easily
lose totally the meaning with such
translation
and we are we are forgetting to make to
make such
uh translation we are forgetting the
other the other that's very important
and other understands uh justice not
as ourselves not as this prevalent uh
prevalent attitude in our own cultures
so
uh in that sense i think that
postmodernism is as well too too
to western to universalist it it
some sometimes uh applying to to be
applied to the anthropology that
gives very good example for example new
anthropology edward cohn
the the scholar there is the castro
when they accept this plurality of the
human
cultures in that sense in that sense
post-modernism is very very
uh very important but as well
uh it is not uh free from some
western universalism and some kind of
epistemological racism that we should
overcome at any price
cool um peter jones you had a few
questions above
um if you can update yourself and ask
them oh
thank you thanks for your your time
professor dugan um
my let me ask a question about um the
scalability the fourth political theory
i'm interested in
um in your your work on the definition
of
the civilization and i wonder about the
relationship of that to
um uh you know scaling the fourth
political theory across
the levels of the social and so i
don't know if you're familiar with uh
you probably are nassim teleb's
principia politica he denotes the idea
of the
fractal scaling of politics as it dear
political commitment can differ
from the family to the community to the
to the nation and he doesn't define
civilization but i think as you do i'd
like to hear that
he says there there's really no scaling
of the political commitments at each
level we might be a communist or their
families
it might be a a liberal in your s
in your city but at your nation be a
libertarian
but so if we look at the sign does that
scale from
i mean i think it does actually why this
is there's some workability here
because dust sign should seem to scale
from
the small to the universal what level
how do you see the you know the
universal if the
civilization is the culture writ large
is there a collective da
sign that some cultures can perform but
other cultures may find inaccessible
will it scale can a civilization
participate
in a collective dust sign
thank you that is a very important
question
uh i have uh written the other important
book
uh on the same uh uh as first political
theory that is called
the theory of multipolar worlds where
precisely i am i'm concentrating
on the explaining the
the the meaning of the pole
of multi-polarity what is the pole and
uh in my opinion the fall is not state
because state is the part of western
political modernity so
paul should be different if we accept
this
multitude this pluralism we should
abandon the concept of
necessity of the state because it's
projection of the same western
ethnocentric racist totalitarian vision
so we should
accept this state optional so in one
in one society in one tradition
state could be the main scale so for
example everything will be
all the uh uh other scaling
can be secondary to the state for
some some peoples and civilization for
other civilizations scaling can be
totally different
without such such a balance so
so how many civilizations
so many forms of scaling
not only uh not only family community
clan class religion
ethnic uh and so on the political
so uh individuals so we can uh
so in my opinion civilization is living
being
or the planet or the planet so we could
apply we couldn't apply uh
for example the condition of living on
the venus
so the planet mass or to the planet
jupiter so we should understand the
constellation the system
maybe there are some values
that we every uh we should we all of us
can share but we we we don't know from
the beginning from the very beginning we
don't know
maybe there are but if we want to arrive
to some global really shared values
we need to ask everybody we not in
numer we need to ask small
indigenous tribes what they think
about justice or scale
or human or marriage or or or sex
or uh or political power
or but there are perahan tribes in
amazonia amazon river that have no
numbers
and we need not we shouldn't regard them
as undeveloped some kind of monkeys
they are human and they have all the
right
to have civilization without numbers so
numbers are not
universal they could not uh count one
or two that means that one or two
calculation is optional for the human
they are human i am insisting they are
human
and only those are monkeys who
think they are not human so i i reverse
that in that sense we can arrive to some
um some major scale
major basis of design to real humanism
to real uh common denominator of these
civilizations
but only after after to accepting
all kinds of societies all kinds of
design
all kinds of culture as full
scale humans and that is not the way
of the uh political modernity that's
always have
some enemy of open society of class
of nations some underdeveloped some
uh uh intervention
for subhuman for liberals today
are all i am subhuman in their rights so
where are they for example levis has
spoken with myself
with monkey precisely so uh that was
very interesting
he he didn't bother to to to read his
own book
and i but i have read his book i i i
have used the
argument he he didn't recognize his his
book
uh i was speaking with myself so because
i am russian i am in putin's lander
and so i am sub-human i i i am fascist i
am
uh that is the way
to by the western universalists deal
with
other and when when they see muslims or
so
poor muslims they don't know yet that
god
doesn't exist don't that doesn't exist
so we will
we will teach them little well it will
integrate them
so but they they they understanding of
human being
in islam is the relation with god that's
more more important scale
than than fabled and political power
relations to god
that means to be muslim man or a muslim
woman
so that is interesting and when we see
or maybe that is
prejudices let treat them correctly but
we could not we shouldn't share we will
re-educate them
and will destroy their humanness islamic
understanding of
of humanness so i i think that scaling
as well should not be universal and
taleb
is as many western or
westernized author
as well who is dealing with the same
universalism
so he he sometimes is interesting
but what is important uh multi-polarity
and concept of civilization should be
taken in the plural
civilizations with f and that means
that we could not use so easily uh for
example the concept scaling
it's good it's better to use scaling
that use
some universal concept for from or for
for
for example uh human rights that is pure
racist and
uh concept human rights that we know
what is human and with we know
what is right we are going to teach you
you you are not human you are
semi-human we will go we will teach you
what really human is what the right uh
is
if you if you protest we will bomb you
with humanitarian purposes
that is the way to to liberal to uh to
deal with
where with other but i think that it's
better to
use the scaling it's better already
better a little bit
but it's not enough
thank you for that um if i can ask one
follow-up question
can i ask for a do you have a sense of
foresight for the end of enlightenment
era
in in the west i mean what would you
suggest
is happening now could there be could
the west be
breaking into several types of
civilizations that we don't yet
recognize as such
you know this is a group in the store we
talk about mimetic tribes
but again writ large there are much
larger forces at work
across the west and the kind of
breakdown of the g7
and the uh war against populism is there
is there a breakup into different
civilizations happening
i think that uh the
enlightenment uh is uh um
has arrived to its end and
post-modernism as well
and uh uh highlighting that
so that we are coming to the end of
enlightenment and i think
that this understanding that we are
arriving
to the end of enlightenment changes not
only enlightenment by as well our
understanding of what enlightenment was
because if something
uh has ended we can't see it in a
whole a whole scale so
there is the speculative realists
i am interested as well in in them
and they nickland for example has
introduced the concept of the black
dark enlightenment dark enlightenment it
is idea that
enlightenment were parasitic racist
things
imposing some slavery concept
or on the other we uh in the west
everybody thought that that was the kind
of arrival of new liberty
the justice equality but
that was the new kind of real
dictatorship censorship
and genocide as such and
these people accelerationist they
advocate that
they they say let's continue
this dark enlightenment so
let be openly uh openly destructive
violent and uh and that will be
the the logical logical uh
end of of all these
uh all uh these so enlightenment is not
so unlike
was not so enlightening maybe it is
completely
different and uh i agree with that i i
don't like and like
don't like an enlightenment at all now i
am working on the series of lectures
to deconstruct the uh the
natural science of enlightenment trying
to find the moment
when the er every uh everything
went wrong and i have identified
this precisely with the abandoning of
aristotle
so i think the aristotle and the
platonism
were the real basis for real science and
atomism introduced against aristotle and
platonism
was the the end of this black
or dark enlightenment in the natural
science as well
that was a kind of new materialist
metaphysic that
has destroyed the real identity of the
west
so i i think that now that is not
uh for example we could not say oh there
was very good process of enlightenment
and now
that this process is in danger that's in
in decline
the problem is we see the reality of the
enlightenment that
never this uh phenomenon was
uh such as we imagined it
to be previously so from the beginning
that was something wrong with that
that was something incorrect that was
something
uh something terrible and now it's
reality
is manifesting and it is
when we see the reality of the essence
of the
enlightenment we uh we were rejected
so that is something for example when we
see the liberalism
is totalitarian we are ejecting we
thought that it was
just a contrary to what now
it's uh it clearly manif and manifested
it is so i think so enlightenment is
over
by the thought of the enlightenment
and the understanding of of
reality of the enlightenment has just
begun
so we are in the first stage of free
rethinking revising what is uh
what was enlightenment and i think from
our revision
and from this understanding of the
reality of the enlightenment depends
the future because we could just deplore
that or try to
to save that and that will uh multiply
the violence and the racism and the
agony
of the wounded dragon of western
hegemony
or we can accept that deconstructed in
in proper way
in order to say what it is to
uh still is to be saved
all right uh so we might have
one more question uh connor if you kind
of mute yourself you had a question
about ecological collapse
yeah uh so i was wondering regarding
uh global concerns uh like what is the
four fourth
political theory's position on
ecological collapse
and the potential dangers of human
overpopulation and then there's a
related
ion that was uh regarding global
concerns such as the environmental
climate
would each state have the highest
authority and how to address this or
would you wish for a
any global institution to have authority
above the nation state which
doesn't seem to be the case yeah
so i think that um
as well first of all uh the ecology
uh is uh uh today uh
so actual because of the
industrialization technology and
uh materialism of the modernity
so the the ecological problem has
come with modernity accelerating more
and more
precisely following the so-called
technological progress so the more
industrialization
more ecological problems but
uh in order to to to to um
solve this problem we could not accept
uh nature as a kind of
um objective or
or objective reality the nature and the
human
uh um they are two poles of the same
of the same being because uh human is
not something
outside of nature and nature is not
something outside of the human
and that was uh forgot forgotten
and abandoned and rejected
with the beginning of the modernity so
in order to solve
ecological problems we could not give
the uh power to solve that to some
uh separate supra national
institution or national institution
because
any kind of super national institution
or national institution will be modern
and modernism as psycho psychic disease
in my
in my opinion that's mental disease
modernity so we could not
give to schizophrenics the right
to cure diseases of
of the humanity because the political
leadership
of on the national or on the global
level
are both there are two kind of
schizophrenic
they are still in the same paradigm of
of maternity they are all totally
totally educated
in the materialism and um
you know atheism and the form
they are the parts of this of the
problem so
we could not solve the problem with
relations between
human and nature with the
wrong products misfits of
of this relation so uh in that relation
was the problem problematic and now it
is
problematic um up to the level of the
destruction of both of the nature of the
human we are
we both are on the on the edge of
a catastrophe and we could not give
the the the power to to solve
this problem to those who are the most
dangerous maniacs who have
created uh or can or
conserved that so we need to revise
the human and the nature we need to we
need
you know we have no technical solution
for ecology so that is my opinion so
uh ecology um should be put
in in the critical context of the
re defining rediscovering the reality of
the modernity that is the only way
not just uh add to fourth political
theory
uh ecological dimension that will be to
to
to simple and wrong i think we need to
go
with first political theory and with
high degrees with
its criticism towards modernity inside
of
very very special metaphysical relation
between human
and not human around us and maybe
to uh as a new anthropologists suggest
maybe to find out the human dimension of
on human and human dimension or in
humans but
that is philosophical solution and
metaphysical problem it could not be
solved technically so that is not about
techniques that about destiny so we are
inside of such crisis ecological
graduates not
just because of some technological
some small technical problem that is
destiny
tech technique is destiny as heidegger
has said
as uh friedrich bjork junger has
explained this
in his beautiful books that is called
perfectness
of the perfection perfection of the
technique
i strongly recommend you that is purely
metaphysical
approach to the problem of technology
all right um so we're gonna
land the plane here thank you everyone
for your questions uh we didn't get to
all of them
um but hopefully we'll have professor
dugan back sometime
um would you like to have any closing
thoughts um
before we uh end today
so there are many interesting questions
about uh
jonas the author of uh
by the way the book of agnosticism very
interesting
so um just uh i i
i uh in order to to close
uh this this um
debates or conversation uh conversation
i um i think that uh um
we are living in very important
important um
important uh moment all of us
and as someone recently has said maybe
we are the last human generation
uh in in the history because the
singularity
and replacement of the human by post
humans
is arriving is is closer and closer
so on us is the great responsibility
and uh that is very very um
exciting um very
challenging to live in in the moment
when the humanity
is put on the question maybe it is
unique unique chance to be born in such
radical chant situation and when we just
deplore
some technical details that we have
a small small salary or
there ask there are karana virus
measures when we are um
dissipating in a small problem and
don't don't affront don't don't
put in in front of us the real
real huge issues uh
we are dealing with so um it is great
waste of of the chance to be born
in the end of time it's it's fantastic
finally it's it's very
demands huge responsibility but
at the same time that is a great
opportunity
because now we need to revise everything
everything
we thought it is already taken for
granted
clear obvious natural self-evident
so all kind of such things
don't exist anymore so everything should
be put on the question and i think that
we are not uh we are not alone in that
we have the huge philosophical tradition
behind us
we have experience of many other culture
cultures and
philosophies and religions and societies
we are not alone
there is the all um all the treasure or
all the heritage of the humanity
of religious christianity judaism islam
uh confucianism taoism post-modernism
anthropology
so phenomenology uh um
so we have so many uh many paths
to explore uh in order to arrive to some
to some
real decision as heidegger has said we
are living in front of the last decision
and that is the the reality that is not
for the leaders because the leaders are
the products
they are mechanical parts uh if we could
not say
oh the this should be decided by
some political elites there is no elite
or modern elite is
totally uncapable uh uh that doesn't fit
absolutely existing elite national
global to
to solve such equations to make such
decision so we
we are all inside we are all invited we
are all
we have this mission ourselves we are
the bearers
of design we are still humans maybe not
for too long
but we are still uh then uh
and that is huge responsibility in front
of all generation
past and the future so that is really
crucial moments
uh and i think that that demand from
us some special efforts you know
we are we should participate in the
greatest uh decision as heidegger
has said or about new beginning or the
ending of what should be ended
beautiful nice way to end today's
session uh i'll make some
announcements in a moment but first
professor dugan thank you so much for
visiting us at the stoa today i hope you
had a good time and we'd love to have
you back uh
soon um okay so
uh we're gonna stop recording in a
moment but uh
if anyone like to hang around uh arielle
is going to do
a post-sense making session she has a
series here at the store called the
dangerous space
where she talks about dangerous ideas
and uh she's going to
have these postmates making sessions
after the event um
so uh ariel do you want to just kind of
briefly say
what that's about so if anyone wants to
hang around
i think we're just going to chat about
this there's like so much stuff here to
process so we'll probably go into
smaller groups then
chat a bit and come back to the larger
group that kind of thing
cool cool uh so upcoming events today we
have some uh
pretty awesome events um derek jensen uh
taking his thoughts wherever they go
he's an android primitivist
um he might not show he just emailed me
saying his wi-fi spotty but
uh i'll let where are some pieces that
know on email what's happening there
um brett weinstein uh he's gonna come in
talk about his unity 2020.
uh raven connolly are you still in the
room uh are you um
you want to meet yourself maybe plug
that yeah
sure hi hi peter um yeah so brett's
gonna be coming in
at 6 30 eastern eastern time and i'll be
interviewing him i'm one of his former
former students so it's going to be
really exciting to talk to him about
unity 2020 and
i think it also ties into some themes
that dugan brought up about censorship
on twitter
that's something that brett has been
facing as well so come if you're curious
about a new political
movement that's happening right here in
america and trying to
uh face the duopoly basically that's
what that's what his project is so join
us later today if you're interested in
that
very cool uh and if you're new here we
we have people from all across the
political spectrum tomorrow we have uh
john
zurzan who is a former confidant of the
uni bomber we have glenn walls coming in
to talk about
uh anarchism uh all this can be found on
the website we have like
tons of events coming up check it out if
you'd like to support us on
uh patreon while we steal the culture
feel free to do that by clicking on the
link
so that being said i'm going to stop to
record we'll go on a bio break
within a minute i'll take ariel in and
then we'll have a post since making
dangerous space session
so thanks everyone for coming
[Music]
play some music